Guide to the Tamiment Playhouse Alumni Oral History Collection OH.031
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Playhouse Alumni Oral History Collection
1952-1988
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Horn, Andrew
LoMonaco, Martha Schmoyer
OH.031
5 Linear Feet in 1 record carton, 1 manuscript box, 2 cassette boxes, 2 CD boxes, and 33 items in a shared cassette box.
28 Quarter_Inch_Audio_Reel
118 audiocassettes
The Tamiment Playhouse was a theater at the Socialist Party's Camp Tamiment retreat in Pennsylvania's Pocono Mountains. This collection consists of interviews containing recollections of the Tamiment summer theater, as well as discussions about the importance of the Playhouse for Broadway. All interviewees were involved in the Tamiment Playhouse, mainly in the 1950s. The interviews were conducted between 1980 and 1988 by Andrew Horn of the Tamiment Playhouse Archives and by NYU Performance Studies graduate student Martha S. LoMonaco for her dissertation and subsequent book on the Tamiment Playhouse, entitled Every Week a Broadway Revue. These interviews are in the form of audio recordings and their transcripts. The collection also contains live recordings of shows at the Tamiment Playhouse dating from 1955-1960.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Martha S. LoMonaco in 1992. The accession number associated with this gift is 1986.006.
Arrangement
Organized into two series:
Series I. Oral Histories
Series II. Audio Recordings of Performances
Historical Note
The Tamiment Playhouse was located at Camp Tamiment in Pennsylvania's Pocono Mountains. The camp was a summer resort opened in 1921 by the People's Educational Camp Society and affiliated with the Socialist Party's Rand School of Social Science. Started as a means to entertain campers, the playhouse became a workshop and creative outlet for theater, dance, film, and television in the mid-twentieth century. Participants included actors Danny Kaye, Bea Arthur, Imogene Coca, and Carol Burnett; directors Max Liebman, Herb Ross, and Joe Layton; choreographer Jerome Robbins; and writers Woody Allen and Neil Simon. Much of the original material performed at Tamiment found its way to the professional stage, Broadway, and television.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room.. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Related Archival Materials
Tamiment Library holds several additional collections related to Tamiment Playhouse, Camp Tamiment, and their parent organizations. These include: Tamiment Playhouse Records (TAM.107), Tamiment Playhouse Photographs (PHOTOS.041), Alexander Cohen Tamiment Playhouse Photographs (PHOTOS.080), People's Educational Camp Society and Camp Tamiment Records (TAM.007.003), and Rand School of Social Science Records (Tam.007).
Scope and Contents
This collection is comprised of sixty-three interviews in the form of audio recordings and transcripts that were conducted between 1981 and 1988 by Andrew Horn of the Tamiment Playhouse Archives and NYU Performance Studies graduate student Martha S. LoMonaco for her dissertation and subsequent book on the Tamiment Playhouse, Every Week a Broadway Revue. The majority of the interviews consist of recollections of the Tamiment summer theater, as well as discussions on the importance of the Playhouse for Broadway. Of note are interviews with Woody Allen, Carol Burnett, Imogene Coca, and Neil Simon. The collection also contains live recordings of shows originally recorded live on reel to reel audiotape at the Tamiment Playhouse dating from 1955-1960.
Camps -- Pennsylvania; Socialism -- United States.; Theater -- Political aspects.; Summer theater -- Pennsylvania -- Pocono Mountains -- History; Jewish entertainers -- United States.; Tamiment Playhouse
- Series I. Oral Histories, 1952, 1981-1988
  Arrangement
  Series is arranged alphabetically by interviewee surname.
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of interviews conducted by NYU Performance Studies graduate student Martha S. LoMonaco for her dissertation and subsequent book on the Tamiment Playhouse, entitled Every Week a Broadway Revue.
  - Allen, Woody, September 12, 1986
    - Original Recording (Box 5, Audiocassette 1)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Allen 1)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Barer, Marshall, March 21-24, 1986
    - Original Recording (Box 5, Audiocassette 2A-D)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Barer 1-4)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Berkowitz, Sol, March 4, 1986
    - Original Recording (Box 5, Audiocassette 3A-B)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Berkowitz 1-2)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bird, Dorothy, January 16, 1986
    - Original Recording (Box 5, Audiocassette 4A-B)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Bird 1-2)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Blaker, Ben, September 27, 1986
    - Original Recording (Box 5, Audiocassette 5)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Blaker, Ben 1-2)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Blaker, Martha and Alex, October 21, 1986
    - Original Recording (Box 5, Audiocassette 6A-B)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Blaker, Martha & Alex 1-2)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bock, Jerry, May 13, 1986
    - Original Recording (Box 5, Audiocassette 7)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Bock 1)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bozeman, Beverly, October 27, 1981
    - Original Recording (Box 5, Audiocassette 8)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Bozeman 1)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Brenner, Yvonne, December 11, 1981
    - Original Recording (Box 5, Audiocassette 9)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Brenner 1)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Burnett, Carol, March 22, 1982; cuid34983
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Duration: 95 minutes
    Carol Burnett is featured on the first 14 minutes of this recording, and the remainder is Public Broadcasting content.
    - Original Recording (Box 5, Audiocassette 10)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Burnett 1)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Carroll, Pat, June 9-July 7, 1986; cuid34984
    Cassette A duration: 65 minutes. Cassette B duration: 63 minutes.
    - Original Recording (Box 5, Audiocassette 11A-B)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Carroll 1-2)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Coca, Imogene, March 11, 1986
    - Original Recording (Box 5, Audiocassette 12A-B)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Coca 1-2)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Connell, Gordon, circa 1980s
    - Original Recording (Box 5, Audiocassette 13)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Connell 1)
  - Cook, Barbara, May 16, 1986
    - Original Recording (Box 5, Audiocassette 14)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Cook 1)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Corey, Irwin, February 11, 1986
    - Original Recording (Box 5, Audiocassette 15A-B)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Corey 1-2)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Daniels, Danny, December 3, 1986
    - Original Recording (Box 5, Audiocassette 16)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Daniels 1)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Deems, Mickey, January 15, 1987
    - Original Recording (Box 5, Audiocassette 17 A-B)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Deems 1-2)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Dooley, Paul, August 17, 1986
    - Original Recording (Box 5, Audiocassette 18)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Dooley 1)
  - Ellstein, Sylvia Regan, February 13, 1987
    - Original Recording (Box 5, Audiocassette 19 A-B)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Ellstein 1-2)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Felder, Blanche (Ganz), April 29, 1987
    - Original Recording (Box 5, Audiocassette 20)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Felder 1)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Frankel, Beulah, March 4, 1982
    - Original Recording (Box 5, Audiocassette 21)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Frankel 1)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Garrett, Betty, circa 1980s
    - Original Recording (Box 5, Audiocassette 22)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Garrett 1-2)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Gildermeister, Rick, October 28, 1987
    - Original Recording (Box 5, Audiocassette 23)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Gildermeister 1)
  - Gladstone, Saul, April 12, 1987
    - Original Recording (Box 5, Audiocassette 24 A-C)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Gladstone 1-3)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Goldfarb, Philip, February 9, 1987
    - Original Recording (Box 5, Audiocassette 25)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Goldfarb 1)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Goren, Lewis, August 26, 1985
    - Original Recording (Box 5, Audiocassette 26 A-B)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Goren 1-2)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Greene, Milton, December 12, 1986
    - Original Recording (Box 5, Audiocassette 27)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Greene 1)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Hack, Moe and Hack Cohen, Paula, September 9, 1985
    - Original Recording (Box 6, Audiocassette 28 A-D)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Hack, Moe and Paula 1-4)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Hack, Moe and Thomas, Bill, circa 1980s
    Scope and Content Note
    The first side/track contains the oral history interview with Moe Hack and Bill Thomas. The second side/track contains a demo recording of music from Member of the Wedding (vocals with piano accompaniment), possibly performed by Marshall Barer, and additional oral history content.
    - Original Recording (Box 6, Audiocassette 29 A-B)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Hack and Thomas)
  - Hack Cohen, Paula, December 14, 1981
    - Original Recording (Box 6, Audiocassette 30)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Hack Cohen 1)
  - Halliday, Buzz, September 26, 1985
    - Original Recording (Box 6, Audiocassette 31A-B)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Halliday 1-2)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Hayes, Dorsha, July 2, 1986
    - Original Recording (Box 6, Audiocassette 32)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Hayes 1)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Hollister, David, January 30, 1986
    - Original Recording (Box 6, Audiocassette 33)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Hollister 1)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Holt, Calvin, July 29, 1986
    - Original Recording (Box 6, Audiocassette 34A-B)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Holt 1-2)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Josephson, Ben, October 30, 1986
    - Original Recording (Box 6, Audiocassette 35A-B)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Josephson 1-2)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Kallen, Lucille, April 27, 1982
    - Original Recording (Box 6, Audiocassette 36A)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Kallen 1)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Kallen, Lucille, March 6, 1987
    - Original Recording (Box 6, Audiocassette 36B)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Kallen 2)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Kemp, Pearl, November 21, 1986
    - Original Recording (Box 6, Audiocassette 37)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Kemp 1)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Kert, Larry, December 5, 1986
    - Original Recording (Box 6, Audiocassette 38)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Kert 1)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Lawson, Sid, October 6, 1981
    - Original Recording (Box 6, Audiocassette 39)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Lawson 1)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Levitas, Michael, April 21, 1987
    - Original Recording (Box 6, Audiocassette 40)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Levitas, Michael 1)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Levitas, Willard, March 24, 1987
    - Original Recording (Box 6, Audiocassette 41)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Levitas, Willard 1)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Lichtenberg, Daniel, April 9, 1986
    - Original Recording (Box 6, Audiocassette 42A-B)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Lichtenberg 1-2)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Liff, Biff (Samuel), July 7, 1986
    - Original Recording (Box 6, Audiocassette 43A)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Liff 1)
    - Transcription (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Meyer, John, February 2, 1987
    - Original Recording (Box 6, Audiocassette 43B)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Meyer 1)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Nye, Anita; Starbuck, James; and Tolkin, Mel, circa 1980s
    - Original Recording (Box 6, Audiocassette 45)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Nye 1)
  - Pockriss, Lee, March 13, 1986
    - Original Recording (Box 6, Audiocassette 46)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Pockriss 1)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Remo, Ken, December 20, 1985
    - Original Recording (Box 6, Audiocassette 47A-B)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Remo 1-2)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Rodgers, Mary (Goettel), September 23, 1981
    - Original Recording (Box 6, Audiocassette 48)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Rodgers 1)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Rosales, Sylvia Marks, April 16, 1982
    - Original Recording (Box 6, Audiocassette 49A-B)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Rosales 1-2)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Ross, Mark, April 18, 1986
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Sandyville Group, August 27, 1985
    Includes Annette and David Leisten, Bess Goldstein, Rose Hochstein, and Mrs. Myers.
    - Original Recording (Box 6, Audiocassette 50A-B)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Sandyville 1-2)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Scheiner, Harry, June 2, 1982
    - Original Recording (Box 6, Audiocassette 51)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Scheiner 1)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Seltzer, Ellen, January 1, 1987
    - Original Recording (Box 6, Audiocassette 52)
    - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd Seltzer 1)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Simon, Danny, December 5, 1986
    - Original Recording (Box 6, Audiocassette 53A-B)
    - Access Copy (Box 4, Cd Simon, Danny 1-2)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Simon, Neil, January 20, 1988; cuid34985; Duration: 23 minutes.
    - Original Recording (Box 6, Audiocassette 54)
    - Access Copy (Box 4, Cd Simon, Neil 1)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Simone, Arlene -- There's a Lady on Stage, February 23, 1987
    This is Arlene Simone's commercially-recorded album There's a Lady On Stage. Songs include: "Quiet Please, There's a Lady on Stage", "You are So Beautiful", "Ain't No Sunshine", "Something Cool", "Over the Rainbow", "Memory", "If and When", "Papa, Can You Hear Me", "Torna A Surriento", "New York, New York", and "Some other Time".
    - Original Recording (Box 6, Audiocassette 55)
    - Access Copy (Box 4, Cd Simone 1)
  - Starbuck, James, December 12, 1985
    - Original Recording (Box 6, Audiocassette 56A-B)
    - Access Copy (Box 4, Cd Starbuck 1-2)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Stich, Faye Stern, July 24, 1985
    - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 095, Audiocassette 57)
    - Access Copy (Box 4, Cd Stich 1)
  - Tamiment Playhouse Performances, 1952
    Contains music by David Hollister and lyrics by Don Meyer. Selections include "I Go For You," fragment of New York opening ("A Wonderful Place to Live"), "Who Needs It," "All Aboard," "I Wanna Make Love Tonight," crossover before sketch "Death of a Streetcar" with Don Meyer and Danny Simon, and "Congratulations Mrs. Brown."
    - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 095, Audiocassette 58A-C)
    - Access Copy (Box 4, Cd Tamiment 1-3)
  - Theodore, Lee, November 10, 1981
    - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 095, Audiocassette 59)
    - Access Copy (Box 4, Cd Theodore 1)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Tolkin, Mel, circa 1980s
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Wagner, Charles, July 9, 1986
    - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 095, Audiocassette 60)
    - Access Copy (Box 4, Cd Wagner, Charles 1)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Wagner, Frank, December 30, 1981
    - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 095, Audiocassette 61)
    - Access Copy (Box 4, Cd Wagner, Frank 1)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Weiner, John, June 3, 1986
    - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 095, Audiocassette 62A-B)
    - Access Copy (Box 4, Cd Weiner 1-3)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 56)
- Series II. Audio Recordings of Performances, 1955-1960
  Series is arranged chronologically.
  This series includes live audio recordings of performances at the Tamiment Playhouse from 1955-1960.
  - Ninth Show, Do It Yourself, circa August 27, 1955; cuid34980 (Box 2, Quarter inch audio reel 1)
    Duration: 89 minutes
  - Tenth Show, People Will Talk at 3.75, September 3, 1955 (Box 2, Quarter inch audio reel 2)
  - Twelfth Show, 1955 (Box 2, Quarter inch audio reel 3)
  - Second Show, Spic n Span, July 7, 1956; cuid1042 (Box 2, Quarter inch audio reel 5)
  - Third Show, Perchance, July 15, 1956; cuid1041
    - Original Recording (Box 2, Quarter inch audio reel 4)
    - Access Copy (Box 4, Cd Perchance 1)
  - Ninth Show, Time Was, August 25, 1956; cuid1043
    - Original Recording (Box 2, Quarter inch audio reel 6)
    - Access Copy (Box 4, Cd Time Was 1-2)
  - Tenth Show, We Promise the Moon, September 1, 1956; cuid1044
    - Original Recording (Box 2, Quarter inch audio reel 7)
    - Access Copy (Box 4, Cd We Promise the Moon 1)
  - Twelfth Show, First Act, 1956; cuid1045
    - Original Recording (Box 2, Quarter inch audio reel 8)
    - Access Copy (Box 4, Cd First Act 1)
  - Twelfth Show, Second Act, 1956; cuid1046
    - Original Recording (Box 2, Quarter inch audio reel 9)
    - Access Copy (Box 4, Cd Second Act 1)
  - First Show, Do It Yourself, June 29, 1957 (Box 2, Quarter inch audio reel 10)
  - Fourth Show, Do It Yourself, July 20, 1957 (Box 2, Quarter inch audio reel 11)
  - Twelfth Show, Do It Yourself, September 7, 1957 (Box 2, Quarter inch audio reel 12)
  - Third Show, High Hopes, July 18, 1959; cuid44916 (Box 2, Quarter inch audio reel 13)
    Duration: 58 minutes
  - Fourth Show, Red Hot / Fifth Show, Isn't America Fun, July 25 - August 1, 1959; cuid44917 (Box 2, Quarter inch audio reel 14)
    Duration: 125 minutes
  - Fifth Show, Isn't America Fun, August 1, 1959 (Box 2, Quarter inch audio reel 15)
  - Happy Medium, August 22, 1959 (Box 2, Quarter inch audio reel 17)
  - Ninth Show, Curtain Call, August 29, 1959 (Box 2, Quarter inch audio reel 16)
  - Rehearsal of Ninth Show, Jazz Fuegue, 1960 (Box 2, Quarter inch audio reel 18)
  - Princess and the Pea, undated (Box 2, Quarter inch audio reel 19)
  - Second Show, Let the Bells Ring, July 9, 1960 (Box 2, Quarter inch audio reel 20)
  - Third Show, Silver Screen, July 16, 1960 (Box 2, Quarter inch audio reel 21)
  - Fourth Show, Round Robin, July 24, 1960 (Box 2, Quarter inch audio reel 22)
  - Fifth Show, Pocketful, July 30, 1960 (Box 2, Quarter inch audio reel 23)
  - Sixth Show, There You Are, August 3, 1960 (Box 2, Quarter inch audio reel 24)
  - Seventh Show, There You Are, August 3, 1960 (Box 2, Quarter inch audio reel 25)
  - Eighth Show, Pocketful of Wry, 1960 (Box 2, Quarter inch audio reel 26)
  - Ninth Show, 1960; cuid34981 (Box 2, Quarter inch audio reel 27)
    Duration: 65 minutes
  - Eleventh Show and Final One, 1960 (Box 2, Quarter inch audio reel 28)